I'm here at Harvard in the office of Steven Pinker.
And he's written nine books and devoted his life
to studying language and cognition and writing.
And so what we did in this interview
is we started off with the really practical stuff.
We started off with his rules for writing.
And what makes him unique is that he's
been thinking about AI since the 1980s.
So if you're interested in doing great nonfiction writing
in the age of LLMs,
well, this interview is for you.
I want to talk about The Curse of Knowledge.
And I want to talk about
this cartoon from your book, which
says, good start needs more gibberish.
Yes.
When I posed the question, why
is there so much bad writing?
Why is there so much academies and bureaucraties
and corporaties?
People's favorite answer is captured by that cartoon,
namely that bad writing is a deliberate choice.
It's in various versions.
It's academics with nothing to say dress up banal ideas
with gobbledygook to show how sophisticated they are.
Or pasty-faced nerds get revenge
on the girls who turned them
down for dates in high school.
People want to erect a kind of cult
that no one else, outsiders, can't penetrate because they
haven't learned the jargon.
I don't think that's the best explanation for bad writing.
Partly, it's personal.
I just know enough people.
I know enough people who have plenty to say.
They're brilliant people.
They have no desire to obfuscate.
They're just incompetent.
They just don't know how to express themselves clearly.
There's something called Hanlon's razor.
Never attribute to malice that which can adequately
be explained by stupidity.
Yeah.
And these are not stupid people I'm talking about,
but it's a kind of stupidity in
not knowing where your audience is coming from.
And I illustrate it with an
anecdote of a conference in technology,
entertainment, and design, better known by its acronym, TED,
where a brilliant molecular biologist had
been invited to present his latest findings.
He launched into what was obvious to
me as the exact kind of talk
that he would give to his peers in molecular biology.
And that,
within about four seconds, he had lost everyone
because he just spoke in jargon without even
introducing what problem he was
solving, why it was significant.
It was launched right into the experiments.
There was a room of several hundred
people from many walks of life, from entertainment,
from design.
And it was obvious to everyone in the
room that no one was understanding a word.
Obvious to everyone except the
distinguished biologist, who was just clueless.
Now, this is not a stupid man.
He was very stupid when it came to
communication, namely, not everyone knows what you know.
Now, the curse of knowledge, a term from economics,
is the difficulty that we all have in knowing
what it's like not to know something that we know.
That is to subtract something from your brain,
put yourself in the shoes of your audience,
whether it be in public speaking or in writing.
Figure out where they're coming from.
What do they know? What don't they know?
And you know what? What I'm talking about?
don't they know?
I think that's the main cause of bad writing.
You get abbreviations and acronyms
that no one has any way of knowing.
You have jargon that is known
only to a tiny little clique.
You have abstractions.
The level of the stimulus was proportional to the intensity
of the reaction.
And what it really means is
that kids look longer at a bunny
than a truck.
So that is, it's so familiar to you
that you don't think it's
worth explaining to people concretely
what they're supposed to be seeing.
So all of these are manifestations
of the curse of knowledge.
Goes by other names, egocentrism, absence
of a theory of mind.
That is a theory of what's
going on in other people's minds.
And if I had to identify
the single biggest flaw in writing
and communication, it would be that.
That's it.
So when you're writing your books,
I know you go up to Cape
Cod and you write for as long
as you possibly can.
Now, I would assume that one way to get around
the curse of knowledge is just to talk
to the kinds of people
who would be reading your book.
Yeah, you show it to people.
So what do you do?
What do you do?
Because you write really intensely.
So when you're writing, how do you get around that?
Well, I do something that
I know is not good enough,
but I do it as
best I can, which is I
try to imagine what it's like for someone
not to know what I know.
That is, I try to cultivate my sense of empathy.
But the problem with the curse of knowledge
is you don't know when you're subject to the curse
of knowledge, because something that seems so obvious to you
that you don't even question whether other people know,
it turns out not to be obvious.
So anyway, I try.
But at the end of the
day, I show it to people.
When my mother was alive, I would always
show her a draft of my book.
Not for the reason that most academics cite,
namely referring to my mother as the most
epitome of a unsophisticated, not very well-read,
not very bright person.
My mother was extremely intelligent, extremely well-read,
and very sophisticated.
But she wasn't a cognitive psychologist.
She wasn't a psycholinguist.
She didn't know what I knew.
And when I write, I don't
write for just a random sample
of the population.
They don't buy my books.
I write for people who are intellectually curious, who
have some degree of education.
However, not for peers in my field.
And so my mother being an example.
But also, of course, when you publish
for a commercial publisher, you have an editor.
And the editor is typically very smart,
but again, not in your field.
And I show it to people in different fields
who are academics.
But it's surprising how insular even academics are when
it comes to other academics.
Sometimes there'll be people here in this building,
in my own department, sometimes my own subdivision
within my own department, like students.
And they'll give me their thesis proposal.
And I just don't know what they're talking about.
Sometimes in my own field, because they've
been immersed in like five
or six people in their lab.
Their supervisor and the other grad students,
a couple of postdocs, and a research assistant.
And they've all been consuming the same jargon,
that as soon as they step outside
that tiny little circle, they're unintelligible.
So even showing it to.
If I'm showing it to a friend who's
an economist, or a historian, or a political scientist,
or an evolutionary biologist, not
being a cognitive psychologist, they'll say,
I'm sorry, but I just
don't know what you're talking about.
Yeah.
In terms of your writing,
you've done so much work looking
at vision and how the brain works.
And it seems like a lot of your writing advice
is informed by that.
Like, I guess if I
were to try to summarize it,
it's like a lot of
our brain and basically the way
that we move through the
world is indexed heavily on vision.
And so writing well means being concrete and helping people
see what it is they're trying to write.
Is that a good way of describing it?
Yes.
And that would be probably the second bit of advice
on the list.
OK.
The first one being, find some way
of getting into your reader's heads.
But don't just depend on
your ability to get their heads.
Actually, get a flesh and
blood person to actually read it
and see if it makes any sense to them.
So that'd be number one.
Number two is, I study language.
And as a writer, I live in language.
Yeah.
But language is kind of overrated in the sense
that what understanding consists of
is not a bunch of words.
It's not blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
But language is a means to an end
of getting people to appreciate the ideas you're
trying to convey, which are
not just a string of verbiage.
And those ideas very often are visual and motoric,
that is bodily, emotional, auditory.
But they're sensory.
Hm.
Or they're even conceptual.
But they aren't just a bunch of vowels and consonants.
Right.
And so constantly allowing your reader
to be able to form a
mental image based on what you're writing
is the next key to good writing.
That is, don't talk about a stimulus
if you mean a bunny rabbit.
Right.
Don't talk about a level
or a perspective or a framework.
Or a paradigm or a concept.
All of which mean a lot
to you in your day-to-day work.
But no one can form an image
of a paradigm in their mind's eye.
So how do you do that?
Like, one thing that you've said
is use for example all the time.
What else can we do?
So often visual metaphors are helpful.
One of the reasons that often the prose
of other eras strikes us as so much,
much more vivid is that.
I was going to say lush.
Lush.
Yes.
Partly because they had the
advantage of writing before there were
several hundred years of academia and intellectuals
inventing terms and abstractions.
And they had to appeal to images that were
part of people's common knowledge.
So instead of saying something like aggression
or antisocial behavior, they might say,
the spirit of the hawk kneaded into our flesh.
Yes.
We wouldn't write like that because we can say aggression
or antisocial behavior.
But that's jargon that a
lot of people are familiar with.
But they weren't always with us.
And before that, there had to be
some way of referring to it in terms
of an image that everyone shared.
And I think that's why
often the writing of previous centuries
just strikes us as so much more
gripping, so much more evocative and powerful
that they had to appeal to.
And that's why we're so proud
of the fact that we have
this kind of visual metaphors.
Yeah.
I've never thought about that before.
Because a lot of the Bibles
like that, I think of like,
I don't know why the
owl of Minerva came to mind.
There's just all of this symbolism in animals.
It always is striking.
And so what you're saying
is a lot of the concepts
that academics and people brought in, obviously,
they're kind of a more efficient way to communicate.
But they do lack that kind of visual quality
that makes writing vivid.
That's right.
And so you can't be a biologist or a biologist
and do all of that stuff.
But you can talk about things like the universe,
or doing the work within the profession.
You have to be able, if you're a biologist,
you have to be able
to talk about things like ecosystems,
and species, and systems, and reagents, and potentiation.
All these concepts that you don't want
to have to go back to basics
and talk about, well, there's a certain amount of chemicals.
And so you have more and more abstract terms
that you could refer to, enormous bodies of knowledge,
just with two syllables.
That's very good.
The problem is that then now
when it's time to convey them
to someone who isn't at the pinnacle of specialization
in your field, because of the curse of knowledge,
you're apt to forget that these abstractions, which
are basic to you, or just
don't even need to be defined,
aren't basic to anyone else.
Hm.
What do we need to know about writing?
And I think that's where you
get the most out of writers,
about how hard writing is.
And I mean it in this way.
Speaking comes so naturally to us,
but then writing is something that
we sort of have to learn.
You watch a kid, and you talk
to a parent who has a 20-month-old.
They're like, yeah, they're speaking now.
They're like, oh, you wouldn't believe it.
They're talking so much.
They're crawling around.
And it's always like, yeah, it's like that.
And then you talk to them who have parents
who have eight-year-old kids.
How's the writing going?
It's like, well, it's going a little slow.
There's not that same excitement.
Why is it that writing
is so unnatural in a way
that speaking is so natural?
What is going on there scientifically
and then practically?
A number of things.
One of them is that in conversation,
you never have two people
that are parachuted on a stage
and immediately have to begin a conversation.
They have some common ground to begin with.
They know why they're there.
They're talking about something that is in the air
that they're both familiar with.
It was the reason for them having
the conversation in the first place.
They can get away with using terms that in context
are perfectly clear, like this and that and the thing
and what I was talking about and she.
Whereas if you are not
privy to that little social circle,
you may not know who they're referring to.
In writing, you're wrenched from the context.
Someone's picking a book up off the shelf,
and they've never met you.
And they may be living in a different country.
You might be dead.
They've got to pick up all of this detail
from what's there on the page, not the common ground
that the two people bring to the conversation.
Also, when you're speaking, you know
that you're speaking to someone.
You know their idiosyncrasies.
You're a little bit better
at avoiding the curse of knowledge,
partly because you get feedback, like the furrowed brow.
The quizzical expression.
The what?
The request for clarification.
I'm sorry, I just don't know what you're talking about
in real time.
And the body language, the engagement.
Even in a live audience, any speaker knows when people
are starting to fidget and drift off,
as opposed to continuing to be riveted.
None of that is available in writing.
Absolutely.
How about this one?
I think generalizations without examples and examples
without generalizations are both useless.
Yes.
Well, and useless might be a bit strong.
But generalizations without examples, I find,
even in my field, 9 out of 10 times,
I just don't know what they're talking about.
It's like, what do you, like, give me an example.
It's too, because a generalization erases detail.
It sweeps over.
Mm-hmm.
It sweeps over particulars.
You often just can't really know what it's referring to.
And the abstract words in a language
just aren't precise enough.
They often have, we have probably 100 concepts
for every word in the English language.
And so a particular word, especially if it's abstract,
won't call to mind a particular referent.
The example pins it down to what's the general ballpark,
what's the ballpark that you're talking about,
what is the generalization or generalization about.
Now, examples without generalizations, it's,
well, why don't you just tell me that?
Like, you know, and your point is?
Yeah.
And apropos of what?
One of my favorite ways to think about this
is that there's always a trade-off between context
and compression.
So if I could wax poetic for
the next five hours about my train
ride to Boston today. But that's fine.
That's way too long.
Or I could tell you, yeah,
it was an easy train ride.
But then you didn't actually get anything from that,
because there's no context there.
And that maybe we're always kind of balancing the examples,
kind of give us that context.
And then the generalizations are the compression.
And it's actually in, like, the swing and the dance
of the two of those
that good writing and good communication
happens.
Yeah.
So for example, if I were
to say that familiar words don't
have to refer to the literal meaning of their parts,
you can understand that.
And you kind of say, yeah, yeah, OK.
And then I say, well, for example, a bathroom
isn't necessarily a room with a bath.
And going to the bathroom doesn't necessarily
mean going to a room that has a bathroom.
Breakfast isn't necessarily breaking a fast.
And Christmas doesn't necessarily
refer to Christ's Mass.
Now, having said that, I think you now
understand what I mean when I say
that the meaning of a familiar phrase
doesn't necessarily correspond to the meanings of its parts.
Hopefully, that now makes some sense to you,
now that I've given you the examples.
Without the examples, you could nod and say,
oh, that sounds plausible.
But you really wouldn't have understood it.
Let's roll with that.
If adults commit adultery, do infants commit infantry?
If olive oil is made from olives,
what do they make baby oil from?
If a vegetarian eats vegetables,
what does a humanitarian consume?
A writer is someone who writes, and a stinger
is something that stings.
But fingers don't fing, grocers
don't gross, hammers don't ham,
humdingers don't humding, ushers don't ush,
and haberdashers don't haberdash.
What's going on there?
Why did you pull this out?
So this is a quote from Richard Lederer.
I deserve no credit for that criticism.
I love this.
I think it's so good.
Lederer has written a number of delightful books,
like Crazy English and Anguished English.
He has a marvelous ear and a fabulous,
marvelous collector of quirks and errors and oddities
and blunders in the English language.
So that whimsical list is quite profound
because it indicates a lot of truths about language,
such as that over time, compositions of words,
compounds or words with a prefix and suffix,
can sometimes drift away from the original meaning.
The case of adultery,
for example, it is related to adulterate.
Namely, to commit adultery is
to introduce a foreign substance,
namely semen into a woman where it doesn't belong.
But that whole connection has been completely lost.
Also, in many kinds of compounds,
there are a number of different semantic relationships.
So for example, olive oil
is oil made out of olives.
Baby oil is oil for babies.
So there isn't a logical, a single logical relationship
between the different parts of the compound.
Language is so ancient.
English itself is, depending on how you count,
maybe, you know, 1,500 years old or more.
But it came from the early Middle Ages.
So it's a very, very ancient language.
It came from Germanic, which came from Indo-European,
and who knows where that came from,
that a lot of words can completely obscure their origin.
You have to go to
a dictionary to find them out,
but they're kind of like
fossils of processes in the language
that are long dead.
You know, how the ER got into finger,
I would have to look
up the etymology to tell you,
but it's not the same as, say, sing-singer,
which comes from the rule that
ER turns a verb into a noun
for the kind of person
that typically engages in that activity.
That's a rule that's still alive
and well in the English language,
whereas we have the fossil record of
lots of rules that died long ago.
When you're writing, like, if
I were to basically map out
almost like a gradient of our conversation,
I'd say like, curse of knowledge, I would almost,
I'm being very haphazard here, I'd say
like equal parts left brain, right brain,
and then we sort of moved into kind
of a left brain side of the conversation.
And then I think of what you've said
about language should be a source of pleasure.
Like, I think of that in beauty, right?
You talk a lot about beauty also in your photography.
You're very interested in that.
That to me is more right brain.
So like when you're writing,
when you're actually sitting down at the keyboard,
what are some of the more right brained,
maybe less verbal concepts that drive your writing?
Well, certainly visual imagery.
That is, can I write?
Can I form an image?
Can I read or form an image?
Euphony, that is sound.
That is, is there some poetry in the prose?
And I read aloud or at least mumble,
or at least mumble to myself my prose,
something that's, again, a highly recommended writing tip.
I didn't invent it.
Often when you read a draft of your own prose,
and if you can't articulate it smoothly,
that probably your reader won't be,
mentally sounding it out smoothly either.
The aesthetics sometimes come from even things like
paying attention to the metrical structure of language.
That is the rhythm.
Oh, tell me about that.
There is a regular rhythm to language
in that it's not perfectly, you know,
tick-tock, tick-tock like a metronome,
but there are beats.
And if you disrupt it too much,
then it does interfere with speech,
but it also interferes with reading,
even though it's just characters on a page.
Even the aesthetics of sibilant sounds,
generally too many chs and ss
make prose a little unpleasant,
and I will often pick a synonym
that avoids the sibilant,
at least too many sibilants in a row.
I'll often go with alliteration,
just because it, again,
there's a little spark of pleasure.
Sense of style.
Sense of style, yep.
Even when it is,
you don't want to make it too conspicuous,
otherwise it starts to feel forced.
But often a bit of alliteration
can just make the sentence roll past more easily.
Why do you think that you,
as much as anybody,
have been the person to kind of
stomp your feet, kick and scream
about the, how bad academic writing
has been over the years?
Like when I think of who has been like,
guys, what are we doing?
You've sort of been one of the front runners.
What about it?
I mean, besides the obvious,
what about it has just bothered you so vividly?
Yeah, part of it is just the sheer waste.
That is, there's an awful lot of really brilliant work,
a lot of really smart people in academia,
and why are they doing it?
Just to entertain each other in a closed little circle?
I mean, taxpayers pay for it.
It should be accessible.
They should give it away.
They should state it in a form that it's accessible.
There's also, when even within the profession,
there's just an enormous amount of wasted effort
and potential for misunderstanding in bad prose.
It's like if I'm reading,
if I have to read something,
it's a student paper,
or it's a paper in my own field,
or I'm reviewing a grant proposal,
or peer reviewing a manuscript,
or evaluating for someone for a grant,
it's like, I'm reading a paper
and I'm evaluating for someone for tenure.
If I have to read the same paragraph
like five or six times
in order to know what they're talking about,
for one thing, I might get it wrong,
then what's the point?
In other words,
why should I have to
read it five or six times?
I'd rather be doing something else.
Come on.
Yeah.
So there's waste, there's confusion.
There's also foregone opportunity for pleasure and beauty.
It's enjoyable to read something that's well-crafted
and it's annoying to read something
that's stilted and turgid and bloated.
There are many reasons,
and it does get under my skin
when academics devote so much brain power
into the scholarship
and then just blow off the essential task
of letting the world know what you've done.
Yeah, it's a true virus in the modern world.
Yeah.
I take a particular interest in it,
not just because I do try very hard,
but even in my academic writing, to be clear.
But since I'm someone who actually
not just studies stuff as an academic,
but studies language,
Yeah.
I get particularly annoyed at people
in the field of linguistics and psycholinguistics
because so many of them are such bad writers.
It's like, you study language.
If what you're studying is
what makes a sentence difficult to understand,
why don't you pay attention to your own research
and make your sentences less hard to understand?
Yeah.
What is it that you love so much
about children's explanations?
Things like clouds are water vapor,
smoke is fire vapor.
Oh, yes.
You do see things...
Yeah, that was from my grandson.
I mean, it's poetry.
It's a new juxtaposition.
There's such a freshness to children's explanations.
Yeah, yeah, because they aren't writing in cliches,
and partly because they haven't accumulated
the knowledge.
They have this massive abstractions,
like the writers of a few centuries ago
who had to grasp for some common image.
Children, without the decades
of acquired jargon from academia,
have to appeal to something that they can see
and that other people can see.
Yeah.
There's a guy who I follow on Twitter
who I've really come to like,
and in his bio it says,
listen to children.
They haven't forgotten how to see.
And I know a YouTuber,
and one of the ways that
she comes up with her ideas
is she has conversations with her friends' kids
who just ask these crazy questions,
like how deep is the ocean?
How high would a tower need to be
in order for us to get to heaven?
And then, like, I have another friend
who, when he was a kid,
he thought that clouds were produced
by those little smoke things,
sort of like chimneys,
so he thought that those were like cloud creators.
And there's such a freshness
to just how children see
and how they talk about things.
And like you said,
they can't possibly think inside the box
because they don't even know the box exists.
Yes, right.
And there were,
there have been in history
various features to remind people
of the originality and the freshness of kids.
There was a regular feature from my childhood
called Kids See the Darnedest Things
from a television host named Ark Lipschitz,
Art Linkletter.
Yeah, I've heard of him.
Oh, you have?
Okay.
Yeah.
In fact, what has survived him
and the feature of the program
is the Say the Darnedest Things
or even the verb the darnedest nouns,
which you'll often see adopted in headlines
and it's become itself a kind of formula,
but he originated it.
Johnny Carson,
the longtime host of The Tonight Show,
would sometimes have features
where he'd read answers,
kids' answers to questions to much hilarity.
How does humor factor into all this?
Into writing?
Yeah, exactly.
Like, and even maybe even the science of humor,
like words that are funnier,
because you have that great
talk from like 10 years ago
where you, I'm going to recommend it.
Yeah, well, there's,
I guess like everything, there's an art to it
because you don't want to,
when it's strained, you get groans
instead of laughter.
Yeah.
So it has to be appropriate.
It can't just be something
that has been repeated so often
that people have heard it 37 times before.
Right.
And humor specifically depends on freshness.
Yeah, it does.
And it also depends,
humor does have much in common with good writing.
There's a line from Hamlet,
which brevity is the soul of wit.
Yeah.
Now, it's a great saying for a number of reasons.
One of them is even the term soul,
as opposed to is essential for wit,
or is important for wit,
or even the essence of wit.
Those are ways that we would say it now,
but the soul of wit,
you have to think for a minute,
soul being the deepest, deepest essence,
but it's a monosyllable,
and it has so much resonance.
Yeah.
I guess that Shakespeare really
was a good writer, wasn't he?
Yeah, I've heard of that guy.
Yeah.
But it's also,
it is true and it's a good example of itself
because it is so brief.
It was reiterated centuries later
in the famous style manual,
The Elements of Style by Strunk and White,
where Professor Strunk,
in lectures at Cornell that E.B. White recalled
and then turned to,
he said,
that the first rule of writing is omit needless words.
Now, again, it's a beautiful example of itself
because there are no needless words in it.
And he said that sometimes Professor Strunk
would be so adamant and so insistent
that this was almost the only thing
you needed to know about writing
that he would just not know
what to do except repeat it.
And he'd say,
omit needless words, omit needless words,
omit needless words.
And he would say,
I'm not going to repeat it.
I'm going to omit it.
And he would say,
And I would say,
I'm going to omit it.
I'm going to omit needless words.
And as with brevity is the soul of wit,
aside from being an example of itself,
it is so true that sometimes
when I have to compress an article
to fit into some fixed space,
especially if I'm writing for a newspaper or a magazine,
it's unlike academia
where you can blather on
with no one telling you to shut up.
When you have to write for a paper,
they'll say,
sorry, 800 words.
And if it's not,
know, 803 words, the editor will chop off three words,
and you don't get to say what they are.
And it can often mangle the meaning.
So you have to actually learn how
to say something in 800 words
or however many words it is.
But what I find is often
just the exercise of squeezing it
into that maximum limit just improves the prose
as if by magic.
It's like, oh, you know, damn,
I have to make this shorter.
And I thought I had said it perfectly.
And often when you do it, you find, you know,
it really has improved in quality,
having gotten rid of those needless words.
Partly it's because of mental effort.
Namely, every syllable, every word
is more cognitive processing by your reader.
You can get the same message in quicker.
That's often less work.
But it also makes it aesthetically more pleasing.
You have to work within the constraints
of the English language.
They
have the melody, the rhythm, the music of the language.
It forces you into, often, into concrete language
instead of woolly idioms and cliches.
Brevity is the soul of wit is good.
It kind of just hit me
how good of a line that is.
It's such a good line.
I've heard that 1,000 times.
But it never punched me in
the chest like it just did.
I got to ask.
I mean, with that, sorry, the
reason I brought it up is,
in humor, it's a soul of wit.
I mean, wit used to mean a lot more.
It meant more than just, you know, ha ha.
It meant trenchantness and appropriateness.
But wit, in the sense of just raw humor,
that's something that comedians know.
You pare down the jokes.
You pare down the lines.
When you're using humor, the shorter, the pithier,
the funnier.
If you drag it out, then you know.
It ain't funny.
You can step on your own punch line.
You can telegram.
You can do the punch line.
So I went to Rockefeller Center the other day.
And there's this, call it
like a big thing, a stone.
And John D. Rockefeller is talking
about his theory of society and the good life.
And it was just remarkably well-written, remarkably
well-written.
And then it's the same thing with the Declaration
of Independence.
There's just some beautiful lines in that, right?
We hold these truths to be self-evident.
That all men are created equal.
It's just beautiful writing.
And what do you make of how old their writing,
it seems like when people think about it,
it's like harder to read.
Thank God that writing's gotten so much clearer and easier
to read.
But at the same time, it does feel
like a kind of beauty
in poetry, a kind of reverence
that I have for the language itself
has been stripped away from the English language at times.
You do sometimes feel that.
Again, Rockefeller is a good example
because he did not go
down in history as a pro-stylist.
Yeah, no, exactly.
Thank you.
That was a very important part of that point.
This was the CEO.
He was an oil magnate.
Yeah, right.
And likewise, I have a quote from Thomas Edison
in Enlightenment Now on how the electricity will
liberate women.
And it's just beautifully written.
Beautifully written.
And this is a guy who spent hours with filaments
and light bulbs.
But he could write like an angel.
Herbert Spencer, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr.
That's a great example.
Charles Darwin.
Yeah.
All these people who were not themselves
professional writers.
They had something else, but
they were very good at it.
So it's an interesting question.
I think one reason is they were trained themselves
on the classics, on great works of literature,
probably because for many of
them, there wasn't the telephone,
radio.
Let alone the radio.
Yeah.
Let alone texting, social media.
The way that you presented yourself
was through your prose.
And so you cultivated it the same way
you kind of arranged yourself in a mirror.
This is how other people viewed you.
But you had this stock.
Because also they were educated on the classics,
they had many good examples to draw on.
But then the third reason
is one that came up earlier
in our conversation.
Namely, since they didn't have the benefit of decades
and decades of writing.
And so they were kind of abstractions and cliches.
And they were kind of exploring virgin territory,
conveying new ideas.
And they couldn't easily reach for a canned cliche.
They had to put new
ideas into forms that their readers
or listeners could understand.
And that forced them to
draw on visual images and metaphors,
and vivid.
Vivid expressions and locutions.
And that is that there's been a process that's
been going on for longer
than a century called informalization.
Where you can see it in
dress, where men no longer wear hats
and women don't wear gloves.
And sometimes you look at a
picture of someone on a hike
from a century ago, and the men are wearing ties,
and the women are wearing long dresses.
They're going hiking.
It must be inconceivable to us.
The fact that people used
to address each other with Mr.
and Mrs. And we're all on a first name basis.
I got in trouble in the
third grade for calling my teacher.
I went to detention for calling
my teacher by her first name.
And that would not happen now.
That's certainly familiar to me from my childhood.
It would be unthinkable.
I wouldn't have gotten that detention.
Actually, it's been like 20 years,
and I still feel the shame
that I fell in that mode.
It's crazy.
It just wouldn't have occurred to us.
Yeah.
You couldn't have done that in a million years.
The fact that taboo language, profanities
are commonly woven into speech, which again,
would have been unthinkable a century ago.
But there is a process of greater familiarity,
of less hierarchy, partly as a byproduct of democratization,
the erosion of traditional hierarchies of class
and education.
There's a kind of
romantic ethos where authenticity, spontaneity
are valued as opposed to putting on airs, thinking carefully
before you do anything.
All of these have led to fancy language
being seen as more pompous, stilted distancing,
whereas the cultural value has changed
toward spontaneity, intimacy, naturalness, authenticity.
So I think many of us,
if we had to put the effort
into crafting prose the way they
may have a century or two
centuries ago, we'd feel, oh, people
are thinking I'm being too fancy.
And you might even perceive you as being too fancy.
And as a result, the conversational vernacular,
as opposed to the elevated, the well-known,
the well-crafted has come to characterize modern prose.
So I got to ask, you
were talking about being able to pull
a cliche or an abstraction.
AI takes that completely to the next level.
And do you feel like
AI then enhances our almost inability
to think originally, for lack of a better word?
Does it keep the trend that we're
seeing, or are LLMs a new form,
and then maybe actually create some new way of communicating
altogether?
Yeah, the output of LLMs is peculiar.
In one sense, it's well-written in the sense
that it tends not to be in academies, in jargon.
The sentence structure tends to be pretty plain in sound.
Even the progression of ideas tends to be orderly.
There tends to be an introductory sentence
and concluding sentence.
So in that sense, it's good writing.
It's bad in the sense that
it is so generic and prosaic.
And you can almost recognize the
output of a large language model.
It's so banal.
Now, perhaps it can be trained.
And perhaps if you prompted it, don't be prosaic.
Don't be plain.
It'll be interesting to see whether it would come up
with any kind of style or freshness.
But it's not the way it's designed.
It's designed.
It's designed to be as a
mashup, as a pastiche of literally
billions of examples out there.
And it's an interesting question why it should be so,
at least why its pro style should be sound.
I mean, I think that's the
best you could say about it.
Whereas the pro style of most academics, most lawyers,
most bureaucrats is not sound.
Why is it better?
One possibility is it's just been hammered into shape
and tuned in.
And the feedback that is, instead of just regurgitating
an amalgam of the reinforcement learning
and the stuff they don't really talk about much
but that might be essential,
that is, they're real human beings
who force it into a five paragraph essay.
The other is that, and this is completely speculative,
we know in visual beauty,
often a composite is more attractive
than the actual.
Right.
The elements that went into the composite.
So that if you take a bunch of faces
and you morph them together, the non-existent human being
that comes out of the
morphing is more handsome or prettier
than all of the men's faces
and women's faces that went into it.
Really?
Take a high school yearbook and you mash together
the several hundred faces and
the result is pretty attractive.
Is that right?
Yeah.
Now, whether that can be true of
prose style, that is, that if you
to eliminate all of the god awful convoluted constructions
and just came up with a kind of
the generic sentence structure.
It wouldn't be beautiful, but it would be clear.
That's a hypothesis.
You've written nine books, you're working on your 10th now.
With LLMs and the way they're going,
if you were to almost rewrite those books starting now,
how would you have written those books differently?
I mean, knowing what we know about large-scale response.
Yeah, knowing what we know about LLMs
and also your sense of where the world is going
and how it's changing, how
the world of writing is changing.
Would you have written the same books?
Probably not.
I think I'd have to
give greater weight to the power
of abstracting patterns from massive amounts of input,
which in the approach that
I was kind of trained in
and that I then
developed of computational cognitive science,
Chomsky and linguistics, classic AI,
was much more organized around rules, algorithms, logic,
kind of logical programming.
It was hard to imagine
how with enough just sheer input
and training, an associative neural network
could extract a lot of information.
Yeah.
And then you have to get sensible ideas and prose
out of this huge unstructured mass of input.
Now, I don't think that shows that the human mind
is a large language model,
because it would be the equivalent of a child
listening to language for 30,000 years
before they could put up their first sentence clearly.
And also kids don't just need to have massive amounts
of text pour into them.
They also are in a
situation where they're not able to
read the text.
They're not able to read the text.
And then it's situated in a
world where they can figure out
what the people talking to them are trying to say,
and they're interacting with the world,
and that's a very different style of learning
than just processing massive amounts of text.
But still, I think I
certainly would have had to reconcile
the intelligence of large language models
with human intelligence,
with more attention to the power of pattern extraction
from large input corpora than I did.
Well, thanks very much for doing this.
Thank you.
It's been a pleasure.